hello ladies and gentlemen I am Matt
from Matt's bookshelf and today we are
doing the next installment of my project
pinchon Series in which I read through
all of Thomas pin Chon's Works in
chronological order and the next stop on
this project is vinand violent published
in 1990 has The Unwanted distinction of
being Thomas pinch's followup to
gravity's Rainbow which many literary
critics consider to be one of the
greatest novels of all time definitely
one of the greatest novels of the 20th
century this book is not nearly as long
as gravity's rainbow it is significantly
more traditional than gravity's rainbow
especially even for pinchon um but
roughly speaking the plot follows
Prairie who is the daughter of Zoid
wheeler who is an ex hippie and counter
culturalist they are currently living in
California um sort of laying low uh Zoid
basically his only source of income is
like a dis mental disability check that
that he gets once a year so he to do
something crazy every year and as a
novel begins he's attempting to um jump
out of a glass window not doing it
because he's the same but because he
needs the money and the novel follows
several characters um intering between
different time periods but mainly
follows a group of hippies and counter
culturalists as they endure nixonian
pressure from the 1960s 1980s and as we
find Zoid and Prairie at this point old
demons are are resurrecting an FBI agent
who was responsible for dismantling um a
former commune that Zoid was a part of
has resurfaced and he's looking for Zoid
so Zoid and Prairie go underground um
Zoid splits off and leaves Prairie with
former friends of his from his hippie
days throughout the course of the novel
Prairie learns about her father um the
counter cultural the counter culturalist
cult she he was a part of as well as um
her mother um zo's former lover who is
sort of Infamous among the group because
she was at one point this like fiery and
passionate leader of this militant film
organization held bent on like showing
the atrocities of police brutality on
the rise with nixonian power with
President Nixon's power however he ended
up turning on this group um because she
was in love with Brock vau the FBI agent
I mean excuse me the f
prosecutor and so throughout the course
of the novel Prairie hears excerpts from
different members of the former commune
she looks at films made by her mother
and sort of tries to piece together who
her mother was and as well as the reader
tries to piece together the relationship
um frazzi had with Brock vond had with
Zoid and had with the community and as
well as what this community exactly was
called pr3 so really how do I feel about
violence I've read V I've read the
crying of lot 49 and I've read gravity's
rainbow at this point so even though I
don't claim to be an expert on Thomas
pinchon I think I have a couple rounds
under my belt and can somewhat talk in a
sophisticated fashion about Thomas
pinchon and about violin mainly with my
own opinions on the book I've had a very
complicated relationship with Thomas
pinchon throughout the series so far if
you watch my V video which I recommend
watching so I think it's pretty good and
I really appreciate all the comments on
that video because I wasn't a big fan of
v and the the pinch on die hards
commented were comments are very
supportive and understanding however
I've read crying of lot 49 soon after a
little skeptical as to whether or not I
would like it and it turns out I
absolutely adored the book I read it six
months ago at this point five months ago
at this point and that ending just has
not left like that that impact of the
ending has not lost impact for me and
then of course at the beginning of the
year the only one of two videos have out
this year um is gravity's rainbow and
you know it's gravity's rainbow it's a
struggle to read at times but my God was
it an incredibly rewarding experience
and the crying of L 49 was in my top
three books I read of last year gravity
of rainbow is almost guarant damed to be
one of the top three books I read this
year and so even though I started off
bad with pinchon as time has gone on I
have grown to really really enjoy his
works and so how do I feel feel about v
v is a more traditional novel as I
started off this video with again when I
say traditional you get to include the
fact it's written by Thomas pinchon so
don't expect or Robert um a James
Patterson novel CU this is not it
violent for me represents um the best of
pin Chon's habits as well as the worst
of pin Chon's habits starting off with
the positives my God this book has some
of the best character work I have ever I
mean not ever but at least with my
pinchan reading some of the best
character work uh the fzi arc especially
with her relationship with Brock Von as
she slowly dis Associates with the um
commune in California
pr3 was very engaging for me I read I
was on rics I was as curious as other
people's thoughts in this book because
it is one of pinch's more divisive
novels um what people thought about that
some people are upset that the leading
reason why um
fzi you know attaches herself to Brock
vond and Associates herself with the
with her commune is because she just
really loves having sex with Brock and
some people uh complained about that
being like oversimplification but I
found to be pretty interesting
personally I thought it was like a you
know it's not like she's trying not like
she finds value in his ideals which
would be kind of lame it's it's like
purely like the animalistic or like
emotional attachment to him that I
thought was interesting and how Brock
Von exploits that is tragic but also
creates one of the more despicable
characters and Thomas pinchon novel and
also Prairie's connection with her
mother and how she forms a bond through
her via the films that she made was very
great a huge part of the novel is making
attachments of people through um other
media for example Zoid still finds
attachment through fzi through his
memories and even in the novel he he has
like this fantasy of her coming off from
the beach and her bikini coming home and
he has like an idealized version of it
but even he realizes like oh in this
memory in the in reality this is when
she left him so that was pretty sad but
also you know has a lot to say about the
two different characters and also with
Prairie as she doesn't really know her
mother that well still having to have
that attachment through the films I
thought was really touching in a way
especially you've looked at photos of
old family members you never got to meet
or
you know didn't meet or if they passed
away when you were really young you know
you have the photos and you you know
create ideas of who the people were and
I think that's captured really well in
violent here I want to read a small
portion of uh a scene where Prairie is
looking at documentary footage um
recorded by frenzy of police brutality
in California in the
1960s at some point Prairie understood
that the person behind the camera most
of the time really was her mother and
that if she kept her mind empty she
could absorb conditionally become fzi
share her eyes feel when the frame shook
with fatigue or feet or NAA F's whole
body there as much as her mind choosing
the frame her will to go out there load
the roll get the shot Prairie floated
ghostly light of head as if fzi were
dead but in a special way a minimum
security Arrangement were limited visits
were limited visits mediated by
projector and screen or possible as if
somehow next real or the other on after
the girl would find a way some way to
speak to her this is probably the most
riveting part of the novel for me which
would also lead me into my first
complaint of the novel and that is I
don't think this book has the right main
character the character of weed who is
this professor at this college who you
know incidentally becomes the leader of
this pr3 commune um and in response and
in in in Revolt to the nixonian
impression he is dealing with the
paranoia of potentially being betrayed
deing the paranoia of not understanding
why he's put in this position he's very
much like a slothrop or an edup and mass
type character where some of that
paranoia is imagine some of it is
extremely real because fzi is the one
causing the paranoia fzi and Brock so
it's interesting in one way that he
takes the paranoia theme and explores it
from a different perspective but at the
same time the weed character and his
tragic downfall because he's eventually
killed due to fi's conspiracy created a
really riveting character for me that I
don't think was explored well enough
he's also like kind of like a Christlike
figure too because he gets resurrected
at one point um there's a whole zombie
plot that is interesting in theory but I
don't think it's executed in a
particularly meaningful way but I want
to read that suction too cuz I did find
it interesting because at first weed
starts off as a very idealized person
but as time go goes on he has to deal
with the real world politics of being a
separate Community against the US
government that has them completely
overpowered um and trying to maintain
that pacifist mentality just like sloth
and just like Ed up a mass the ideals
remain with them but they become more
cynical once he would have proclaimed
because in this country nobody in power
gives a about any human life but
their own this forces us to be Humane to
attack what matters more than life to
the regime and those it serves their
money and their property but these days
he was saying it's wrong because if you
pick up a rifle the man picks up a
machine gun by the time you find some
machine gun he's all set up to shoot
Rockets begin to see a pattern between
these two replies something had happened
to him he was still preaching Humane
Revolution but seemed Darkly exhausted
UNH hopeful snapping at everybody then
apologizing if anybody caught this
change it was much too late to make a
difference they still came trooping up
the alley to Rex's place in Las nalgas
like ducklings looking for a mother surf
somewhere hidden in the fog didn't crash
so much as collapse on itself wetly over
and over though we lived there Rex
didn't show up much at these gatherings
anymore having finalized his own plans
to fly off to Paris enjoy whatever was
left of the Vietnamese section of the
fourth International it'll never work we
told him you're an Ango who will trust
you
I really think the novel would have been
perfect if it followed weed and it ended
with his death because my God this is
out of the four novels that I've read
from pinchon so far this is the worst
ending my biggest complaint with v is
that I felt like it was a fairly shallow
book that was that in which he used very
dense and vague Pros to give up the
illusion that something more interesting
was happening that's my hottest pinchon
take so far and I expect that to
probably be the hottest take I'll have
with the with uh him as an author and
especially as with a first readr of his
stuff the ending of this book is
so dumb not dumb but it's it's a happy
ending and I understand because all his
novels up to this point of had sad
endings like maybe he just want to have
a happy ending but he could have just
been this gut punch and he you know he
held his hand and said it's not even
just the fact that it's simple ending
but the fact that the ending is so dense
with just paragraph after paragraph It's
a Long chapter and it just serves no
real purpose to be as long and as
convoluted as it is in my opinion I
won't go into spoilers for that part it
doesn't ruin the book but it left a sour
taste in my mouth and what ultimately
leaves this book as being in my mind
quote unquote mid also pinch's comedy is
a bit Hit or Miss for me here he thinks
these two criminals SL mechanics named
blood and vatto are just like the most
hilarious Duo of all time and I think
they are the opposite of the most
hilarious do of all time and some of
their comical scenes go on forever and I
did not enjoy them there's just so much
going on in violent and I think some of
it is due to the shortness of the
novel but it just feels like whereas
gravity's rainbow had so much in the pot
with all these crazy ideas and to a
certain extent all of them
feel well realized or you know realized
enough vinin feels like a lot of wasted
potential in many ways to me I know that
Thomas Anderson is making a movie on
this and I'll be very interested to see
how it turns out but at least how this
movie how this book is structured it
doesn't really fit the movie format so
I'll anticipate it with baited breath
there and so yeah those are my thoughts
on violin interestingly enough um
Leopold Bloom sorry Harold
Bloom if you watch my 's videos you know
that I constantly called Leopold Bloom
Herold Bloom and now that I have to
reference Harold Bloom I call him
Leopold Bloom um Harold Bloom called
this book a disaster he is a huge pinch
on supporter he was a huge pinch on
supporter and he calls um I think Mason
the Dixon the best book in the 1990s did
not feel very highly about violent and I
don't feel as strongly negative against
him against this book as he does but at
the same time I also view the book as a
ton of wasted potential but speaking of
Mason and Dixon that book is next I'm
not in a huge rest read it I will try to
have it done by July I will be doing
some traveling over the summer but
expect it hopefully in July or August
but in the meantime I'll try to make
videos that are not related to Thomas
pinan I apologize I've just been so busy
especially in April in May I'm hoping
that in June my schedule will clear up
with the end of the term and that I can
start making more content again but I do
really love doing project pinchon and I
really don't want to stop because now
I'm halfway through halfway through I
have only four more books left two of
them are his longest books I think so
from a page count perspective I'm not
really halfway through but whatever
we'll get through it so thank you for
watching um if you made it this far I
appreciate it I have Instagram in the
link below check out my project pinchon
uh playlist as well and check out film
frauds I do with carless Wonderland he
still makes content I just wish we got
like 120 of the views that he gets on
his YouTube channel I'm very happy with
film FRS I think it's a really great
podcast obviously I'm a bi's perspective
but I would appreciate it if you gave it
a chance so thank you and I will see you
in the next video goodbye